this is a quick video about how to parse
multiple documents from a single yaml
multidock stream what do I mean by that
somebody wants me to go to Taco Bell
already um so here you can see this this
is we talked about this before I did
another video on why you have to be
careful of these things this is a multi
multip multiple document stream and it's
not completely intuitive some of you may
try to parse this and you you know you
just just do the unmarshal thing without
doing this so the first thing to take
away from this is um we want to get more
than one document at a time
so uh let me see here if I can show you
what I'm talking
about kind of lost here here okay so
parse um here's how you do it okay so if
you want to parse this is an RX Rob
yamel by the way I'm about ready to
committed it's not ready yet but so
parse pars is a multi do Amel into
into
Robert slice of rooted yaml nodes and
we'll talk about the value of yaml node
later but you'll notice rather than just
unmarshalling it uh we are pulling it
using a
decode now this code is not finished and
I'm going to actually finish it here
because I want to show the problem now
ultimately this is going to return
nodes uh to do uh all the
rest um because we're going to return at
a slice of top level document node
references that look like this so when
they come out um they're going to be you
know we want the kind to be a document
and we want it doesn't have a value and
then that's this in this case there's
one specific thing now what does that
match with that pairs with this first
document here uh right here right so
that would be uh all of that right there
right and we could dump uh this so that
is the document no that's the parent and
then the first item of content within
there and this is something we go go
into when we diving into what what if
you want to know about that you have to
read about yl. node um but then we're
going to jump
into
uh we got our decoder in there okay so
where's our test code did I lose my test
code looks like I did yeah all right so
Yore test oh no there it
is bad Rob all right so here's our test
code and let's see just for giggles and
GS what what is the what is the first
item under there right so let's say so
we have a documented one um let's print
out the doc doc
content zero we know it has one item in
fact they all are going to have one item
actually almost all of them um that will
print NE if there's not there so let's
actually
do uh child let see how about content
zero uh doind and we'll just do that
just for
now.
kind
and we have a a way to look up the
strings that we added because otherwise
they're just
constants so what does that
produce so we can see that the
encapsulating node is always a document
and the important that's really
important because we need to have those
metadata and stuff associated with that
and then we have value the length of the
content is one and the top level is
mapping um in this particular case I
mean this is a generic test right here
um but so yeah don't do that don't do
what wil this posted please don't do
that it's a really bad mistake um it's
really
really people there is a ton of crap all
over the Internet with regard to yaml
and it's all wrong and be extremely
careful especially with go um so by
parsing this node um and I mean I'm not
you know thank you for contributing but
all right so nodes. we see that we got
the mapping right now if I wanted to we
can dump out the first value so let's
try that let's do doc. content
zero um uh do content this is I'm I'm
just kind of jumping right in I happen
to know that a mapping the first item of
a mapping is uh is is the value right so
content uh Z do content
z uh Dov value and this is these are
leaps these are leaps in the not Tre um
that will be a value so we should see a
value there so we see that its value is
a string and the String's value is
title and but we don't have the values
and everything these are all the other
things this is actually a scaler and
that is the inferred tag from that um if
we look at number one you can probably
guess what it's going to
be uh we're going to have to delete all
this out of our Tesa because the whole
point of this video is dealing with
multiple documents and this is very
specific to that document so here we see
the
value for the first scaler which is also
a node the scaler key is a node and by
the way you can have non
string keys in yl people assume their
strings all the time that would be
wrong I'm not creating ml parser I'm
fixing the one that exists um so content
one value string yate markup okay that
again to look at the source data that
we're pulling that from here is that
data right here right and uh so so
content two would be food
content three would be bar and then it
would be the end and then we have a new
document well how do I get this next
document you know how do we continue to
parse down here this is the thing that
really blows people away they don't know
how to do that they don't know how to
decode multiple documents in the same
string and the only way to do that my
friends let me clean up my test a little
bit the only way to do that is with the
decoder itself and I'm going to show you
what I mean by that right now so by
using the the decoder here we can call
it multiple times and every time you
call it it will parse the next document
in the in the list okay so so we have
this if the a equals nil thing right and
then we just added the one node but what
we really need to do is we need kind of
a loop here right we need some kind of
loop here that's going to get us a new
uh a new one every time right we don't
know quite what's going to go in there
yet but we know that every time decode
gets called it's going to do a thing
well so here's the question how do we
know we're
done right how do we know we're done
well you can say Well Mr Rob we can trap
on error right right now if we have any
error at all
we we're done right but what if it's a
parsing
error so the answer is that we actually
have to check so if we don't get a node
at
all
right um so if if we
decode well let me let me think here
so first of all if if we decode it into
node and node turns out to be nil
that means something went wrong with the
parsing
right I happen to know from experience
that that can happen this is very weird
case right because we just assigned an a
thing here but there are really rare
cases where the node after it passes
through decode will will actually be nil
it'll be a nil
pointer so there's kind of a weird Edge
case here where you have to do if node
equals
nil continue
and what that'll do is that'll send us
so if there was anything wrong part
saying that we're still we we don't you
know we're still we're not done yet
right we're not done decoding there
might be other stuff there to
decode and so the other thing we need to
check for is what type of error is it so
if
errors is
error um if error equals
error
i.f and we're going to go ahead and
break
so so there we go we have we can go
check for this so this says if the error
is an end ofile error then we're that's
that's a nice happy error and we're good
to go we can be done right but if it's
anything else if then if it's any other
this this would be a parsing error right
we want to return that so that now
covers Us and now we should get multi
documents in our test so if we go over
here to the
test um then you know we can go ahead
and attempt to do this but now we're
getting panics for different reasons
right the reason that Panic is happening
is because there is stuff in here that
doesn't have a Content so for that we
have to get rid of that that should get
rid of our Panic should Anyway come on
Robbie what's going on here let's see
index oh well we can't to check the
length of a thing that doesn't
exist so that's the reason for
that yeah okay how's that one that help
us no we're still bad index out of
range what are we doing here example
that
goes uh yeah so so here we have no.
kinds doc
value what do we have we have another we
have another n pointer
here index at a range
on line 140
one oh oh oh oh oh oh
oh um that's because for some reason it
didn't oh
whoopsie yeah I should have returned
here or should have returned early from
that that will that will present the
Panic okay there we go uh level lion 14
found character that can cannot start
any
token line
um let's see one this is another thing
too that the yaml errors that are
produced are specific to the document
and so you don't know what document it
was referring to that since this is line
17 uh I'm guessing I don't think it's
the
stream let's try so one two three three
four five six
s that would be I know if I had line
numbers on it would be better I know oh
right right um I know what this is yep
there it is I knew that that's a go
problem you see how I mixed up the
spaces in the tabs in my
sample yeah you got to be really careful
with that in go because go loves to
replace things with tabs that are wrong
in that case we made it wrong so there
we go that that parts that's what we
expect
Ed uh that was set list by the way and
then set no list turn it back off um
tror that in vs
code uh anyway
so I'm sorry for this s word um value we
still want to see uh the length of
content let's try that this actually
should not have been an error that's why
I was kind of confused length of node do
content all right
um doc.
content uhhuh all right so we see that
there's one item in the first item okay
so now we have a problem right because
now our test is only showing us the
first document it's not showing us all
the documents so we need to Loop through
these so for for uh
for uh
doc range
docs and put all this in
here uh okay so there we go we got all
of our documents you can see that
they're all documents though uh do they
have do they all have a Content length
of one yes every single one of them has
a Content link of one which means that
we can then put we can grab what the
type is so we can do content zero what
is this means that every one of those
documents has its own content right and
we're going to report on what that is
what kind it is which we can
do so we can say
content uh zero
doind and again we've we've we've
created a a strings mapping map
um just to keep it so we can see what's
up so so now we
have um well there we go okay so you see
we have a map whoops why is there
a yeah we don't need that all right so
here we see what we were expecting we
see that that's where we kind of are
looking for the type right so the first
one
is we have a document and then the first
item in the document is a
mapping uh the next one is a also a
mapping the third is a mapping the
fourth is a scaler it's just a
scaler and I I want to show you one of
the errors
actually um and then this last
one uh is a sequence and this last this
one is a mapping um let me show you why
that's an error though this is actually
an error in the V3
Library um let's switch these two let's
make this one be the last
one um so as you can see this is a
scaler I talk about that in another
video and but this guy is broken it's
broken because it says it's a mapping
check it it says it's a mapping and it
shouldn't be it should be a
string and the reason for that is
because there's some kind of detection
going on inside of the library that
ignores the
tag and and the thing that's really
crazy about this is if you actually dump
the tag for the type let me show you
we'll dump the short tag for this um
so we'll do short tag we can do short
tag or long
tag um node dot uh let's see doc do
content
zero do short
tag this this looks up the short
tag and you see
this this this sees the short tag as a
string but I mean it's even worse watch
this long
tag
um this is the supposed to be the yaml
specification tag that goes with
it and this is this this is totally
wrong
I mean it's totally totally wrong the
the first item of the document is a
mapping according to the yamel parser
but the short tag is defined to be a
string and its long tag is inferred to
be a string even though it says right
there that it's a mapping that is a bug
that is a legit 100% bug in the yam V3
parser and I don't know how to fix that
what that should have done let me let me
show you why this is a problem
because if it had actually parsed it as
a scaler the way it's supposed to do
then it would have produced a
value
right but but the value is wrong it's
totally
wrong because it's supposed to be
this I'll show you so the value for a
leaf node in this case should be the
content of itself so see how the value
is empty
but look at the value for a scaler up
here even the one that's on the same
line as the divider the value is I'm a
valid scaler
string the value down here according to
the AML
specification should have
been should have
been a string that says I'm
broken that's what it should have been
so if we were going to actually pass
this test actually let's do that let's
let's let's dump all this this stuff in
here and then I'll I'll I'll take this
this use case out and because I I want a
test case I want to create a test case
for this error because I want them to
fix this this is a bad
problem um let's let's actually put that
in our our example test
here
so um I'm going to dump all that in here
ah okay give me a second here it's going
to take just a
bit
output all right so let's
do um sorry let's
see uh test output test yeah all
right
oops all right now what is our test our
test going to pass or
fail yep we're still we're still
uh how how come we're failing did I do
something
wrong what are I missing
[Music]
here the value output equals
value that's a lot of output normally I
would have I would do each one of those
things as a separate output value or I
would write it you know not use an
example test for this but the we missed
we missed something up here we missed
the kind of
actually yeah we missed a kind document
on the first line I
think yeah we did kind
document that should
pass nope still not
passing yeah kind
document kind document kind
document it might be uh out of order
actually
no no no no it wouldn't that's ordered
it's an ordered
list huh I don't know that's a lot of
output so I mean that's not the point of
the video how to write a good example
based test um I just wanted to summarize
that for everybody I'll go ahead and fix
this test up on my own but that is
that's the state of things um the
takeaway from this video is if you want
to properly
decode a yaml multidock stream then you
have to call decode multiple times and
number one you have to check for a nil
value getting put into the node
reference which is weird but it's an
edge case and two you need to make sure
to look for the error that is end file
which is a happy healthy error and
that's when you should break that's how
you know that you're done with incoming
yaml data doc streams uh also know that
um that tags are broken uh in some edge
cases so if you're depending on the yl
V3 parsel and you're using extensive
tags in your in your yl which honestly
in 2024 why are you doing that just use
yl like Json and call it a day maybe use
aliases there's other videos on that but
hopefully that'll give you a sense of
how to iterate through and how to parse
each one of the documents in a multidock
string um you I think one of the morals
of the story here is stop assuming that
anything with a do yaml suffix is a
single yaml document a lot of times a
yaml file has multiple documents in it
especially in the you know the cloud
native world so stop assuming that and
start parsing with the assumption that
there's multiple documents in there
unless you're absolutely sure that's
only going to be one document that's all